What
we're today's דף daf, *Daf* is כ עמוד א kaf amud aleph.
*Chaf Amud Aleph*, of course, and we pick up where do we
pick up? Hold on one second.
We pick up five lines from the top. So we had just
been talking about the whole cases of about when do you assume
that an animal that you bought when you know what you have
to can you assume it has never been birthed, definitely gave birth,
or it's doubtful. So we now quote a ברייתא Baraisa, *Baraita* that
revisits the issues of the משנה mishna *Mishnah*, spells them out a
little bit more. So top again of כ עמוד א *Chaf Amud
Aleph*, five lines from the top, beginning of the line. תנו רבנן
*Tano Rabbanan*, a Rabbi taught: עז בת שנתה ודאי vadai לכהן *Ez
bat shnata vadai lakhohen*. If it gives birth, a goat within a
year, again you bought it from a non-Jew, you don't know what
its history is, so you can assume it's definitely the first birth,
and it definitely goes to a כהן cohen *Kohen* and is brought
as a קרבן korban. *Korban*, there's no doubt. מכאן ואילך ספק Safek,
*Mikan ve'eilach safeik*, it's doubtful. And the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* yesterday dealt
with the question about why can't you assume it definitely has given
birth, but there's enough of a basis for doubt, so we play
safe, so the ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael* keeps it, but he waits for
it to get a מום mum. *Mum* and he redeems it. Similarly,
רחל בת שתים ודאי vadai לכהן *Rachel bat shtayim vadai lakhohen*. If
a sheep gives birth within two years, it's definitely the first birth,
definitely goes to the כהן cohen. *Kohen*. מכאן ואילך ספק safek? *Mikan
ve'eilach safeik*, from that point on it's a doubt, and you keep
it and wait for it to get a blemish. פרה בת שלש
ודאי vadai לכהן *Parah bat shalosh vadai lakhohen*. A cow that gives
birth within the first three years, it's definitely the first one. מכאן
ואילך *Mikan ve'eilach*, and from that point on, ספק safek, *safeik*, it's
a doubt. חמורה כפרה kapara *Chamora keparah*,
and a donkey is like a cow. Okay. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yosi be-Rabbi Yehuda*, by the way, it's interesting just visually, if
you look at those last three lines, do you see how all
the words line up? You know, בת בת בת *bat bat bat*,
you know, שנתים ודאי vadai ודאי vadai ודאי vadai *shnatayim vadai vadai
vadai*, okay. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yosi be-Rabbi Yehuda omer*,
חמורה בת ארבע שנים *chamora bat arba shanim*. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yosi be-Rabbi Yehuda* says no, donkeys actually don't give birth prior
to their you know, if they anywhere up to four years would
be the first birth, presumably it only gives birth between its third
and fourth year. So that in itself is fascinating, right? I mean
you would think that that can be observed anyway. So עד כאן
דברי *Ad kan divrei* רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*. This is
the words of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael* that he says
that you base yourself
on when is the first time that it would have a live
birth. כשנאמרו דברים לפני *Keshenemru devarim lifnei* רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi
Yehoshua*, when this was told over to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi
Yehoshua*... it's fascinating like the way you know it's said, like it's
not just that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* responded, but clearly
it had been reported, and when it was said in front of
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*, אמר להן *amar lahen*, he said
to them, those who had reported this, צאו אמרו לו לרבי ישמעאל
*Tze'u emru lo le-Rabbi Yishmael*, go back and tell רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*, טעית *ta'ita*, you erred. אילו בוולד גמור בהמה נפטרת
*Ilu be-velad gamur beheima nifteret*, if the animal would be exempt from
בכורה *bechorah* only because it gave birth to a live child, then
היה כדבריך *haya kidevarecha*. Then you would be like you said, then
you're right that any let's take the first case, a goat, if
it gave birth in the first year, certainly had not given birth
before. If a sheep gave birth in the second year, it certainly
had not given birth before. So you'd be right if that were
the case. אלא Ela, כבר אמרו *Ela kvar amru*, but the reality
they said, סימן הוולד בבהמה דקה טינוף tinuf, *siman havelad bibeheima daka
tinuph*, that it's considered to be birth for a grazing animal if
it just has this type of a, you know, smelly discharge, something
that somehow they you know it's not just smelly, it's not urine,
I mean, but anyway, something that they knew clearly indicated that it
was a miscarriage. ובגסה שליה *Ube-gasa shilya*, and with a large animal,
a cow, it would be a placenta. ובאשה שפיר ושליה *Ube-isha shapir
veshilya*, and for a woman, a fetus or placenta. Now, meaning that
an animal once it gives has a miscarriage is exempt from בכור
bechor? *bechor*. So it's possible that this animal that you're seeing is
in that let's say the goat gave birth in its first year
is indeed, I agree with you, the first live birth of this
goat, but you don't know that it had a miscarriage earlier on.
And if it had miscarried earlier on, it would be exempt from
בכור bechor *bechor*. Okay, so we're going to see in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* what their debate is about because that seems to be
like a very cogent argument. אלא *Ela*, so rather, עז שטינפה בששה
יולדת בתוך שנתה b'toch shnasah. *az shetinfah be-shisha yoledet betoch shnatah*. I'm
sorry did I skip a line? אלא ואני Va-ani, *Ela ve-ani*... okay,
so that's first what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* said back.
And then he said, ואני אין אני אומר כן *ve-ani ein ani
omer kein*. Now that's, as we're going to see the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* frames this as, what I just said back to you רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*, that's the tradition I have regarding בכור
bechor. *bechor*, that because the animals can have these miscarriages, you can't
assume firstborn. But I personally, not what I received from my רבי
*Rebbe*, but I personally don't say it exactly that way. Here's how
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames this, it sounds almost identical. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to analyze what's the difference. Here's the way
I would respond to what you said. אלא *Ela*, here's how I'd
say it: עז שטינפה בששה יולדת בתוך שנתה b'toch shnasah, *az shetinfah
be-shisha yoledet betoch shnatah*. If a goat miscarried within the first six
months, it can still give birth within the first year. רחל שטינפה
בשנתה יולדת בתוך שתים *Rachel shetinfah bi-shnatah yoledet betoch shtayim*. And if
a sheep miscarries in its first year, it will still give birth
in the second year. Now that just seems to be clarifying his
point that it might give birth in the first. had miscarried before,
might give birth in the second year and had miscarried before, but
he is actually saying limiting the scenarios under which this could happen.
Only by a goat it would only have happened if it miscarried
within the first six months. By a sheep only if it miscarried
within the first year. So that will allow for us to distinguish
between certain types of cases we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara
So the point is basically the same, I admit it's the first
birth but it might have been a miscarriage but what then he
added personally was a clarification of how that could have occurred. So
we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara As the גמרא Gemara
continues. Okay, so that's what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, said back. And
now we have אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva said, אני לא באתי לידי מדה זו. Ani lo bati lidei
midah zo. I haven't, you know, I'm... I haven't come to this
discussion. Meaning, I, you know, I'm not getting into this whole issue
about miscarriages and whatever. I, you know, I don't know about any
of this. So what do I know? I know אלא כל שידוע
שבכרה אין כאן לכהן כלום. ella kol sheyadua shebikra ein kan lacohen
klum. If you know for certain it gave birth before the כהן
cohen has no rights and you don't even have to wait for
it to have a blemish in order for you to eat it.
וכל שלא בכרה הרי זו לכהן. Vekol shelo bikra harei zo lacohen.
If it definitely has not given birth it goes to the כהן.
Kohen, ספק, safek. and if there's any doubt, יאכל במומו לבעלים. yachel
bemumo labaalim. You eat it with the blemish to the owners. Now
it sounds like what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, of course everybody
agrees with that principle. The only point we were trying to say
is, is there a way to know for sure without direct observation?
Can you know for sure based on, you know, what age it
was when it gave birth? So it sounds like what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is saying is, you know, I'm not so fancy, I
don't know if I can trust this, this, you know, these your
principles here. I need direct observation. At least that sounds like what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying. If you know for sure it's
one way, so directly know, if you know directly the other way,
it's the other. All these other cases are just in the big
question mark category and you have to treat them as a doubt.
Now we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara whether the גמרא
Gemara translates רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that far-reaching, but it sounds like
it because he doesn't want to get into this discussion at all
and he says אני לא באתי לידי מדה זו. Ani lo bati
lidei midah zo. Like, you know, I, you know, I don't get
into these these details. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara now
explains their three-way debate. Okay, so במאי קמיפלגי Bimei kamifligi רבי ישמעאל
Rebbi Yishmael ורבי יהושע. veRabbi Yehoshua.
First we're going to focus on the first two opinions. רבי ישמעאל
Rebbi Yishmael that says you base yourself on one year, two years,
three years, and then רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that said you forgot
about the possibility of miscarriage. So what are they debating? רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua seems to have a very cogent response. So the גמרא
Gemara says the most obvious possibility is maybe רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael
feels that miscarriage is not does not exempt. Maybe he feels only
live birth exempts. That would be the obvious way to explain the
debate. So לימא בטינוף פוטר קמיפלגי. leima betinuf poter kamifligi. Maybe they
debate whether טינוף, tinuf, here just טינוף, you know, is again means
a smelly discharge but what it really means here is miscarriage. So
let's say they basically debate that question. Does a prior miscarriage exempt
the next first live birth from בכור? bechor, דקמיפלגי dekamifligi
רבי ישמעאל סבר טינוף אינו פוטר. Rabbi Yishmael savar tinuf eino poter.
He says it does not exempt. It's so, you know, and you
need to be it's בכור bechor. as long as you're the first
this animal's the first live birth that's sufficient. רבי יהושע סבר טינוף
פוטר. Rabbi Yehoshua savar tinuf poter. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua holds
no, that miscarriage exempts, right? Because that's what he said back. If
it was only live birth you'd be right but what about miscarriage?
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. אי דחזינן דטינוף או דטניף,
I dechazinan de tinuf oh de tanif, if we saw it miscarry
דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דטינוף פוטר. dechulei alma lo pligi de tinuf
poter. Everybody would agree, which is funny, right? The גמרא Gemara at
certainly the easiest thing to say is they debate whether miscarriages exempt,
but isn't פטר רחם, peter rechem,
doesn't it have to be a פטר רחם?
peter rechem? Well that's the point. So presumably the גמרא Gemara understands
that the פטר רחם peter rechem cannot allow for even a prior
miscarriage. So, you know, so although it would have been the easiest
explanation, the גמרא Gemara really right actually sort of takes it, you
know, as a given that that can't be, that פטר רחם peter
rechem has to mean that it's not just the first live birth
but that there's nothing preceding. And therefore it forces it into a
more nuanced debate here, because in principle the גמרא Gemara says it
has to be they agree miscarriage exempts. והכא בחוששין לטינוף קמיפלגי. Ve
hacha bechoshishin letinuf kamifligi.
The question is not whether miscarriage would exempt but do you have
to be concerned that that might have been what have happened? How
much do we have to raise that possibility? How much does that
create a ספק? safek. And everybody agrees that if an animal gave
birth within one year, the goat, it's for certainly its first live
birth. So how much is the possibility of a miscarriage enough to
create a ספק, safek. which is similar to our discussion yesterday, which
is how much of a, you know, a small percentage do we
have to worry about? Okay, so that's the question. כי פליגי Ki
pligi
where are we? דטינוף דכולי עלמא לא פליגי. De tinuf dechulei alma
lo pligi. והכא בחוששין לטינוף קמיפלגי. Ve hacha bechoshishin letinuf kamifligi. רבי
ישמעאל סבר אין חוששין לטינוף. Rabbi Yishmael savar ein choshishin letinuf. I'm
not concerned about miscarriage, it's rare enough that that's not something that
would get this out of the category of being definitely a בכור.
bechor, ורבי יהושע סבר חוששין לטינוף. veRabbi Yehoshua savar choshishin letinuf. And
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no,
it's enough of a basis for doubt and you have to play
it safe and, you know, and you don't give it to a
כהן Kohen. and you wait for it to have a מום. mum.
So the גמרא gemara, says one minute. ולו חייש? Veloh chaish? How
could you tell me that רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael is not concerned
for the possibility of miscarriage? והא אמר רבא Veha amar Rava did
we just say at the end of yesterday's דף, right? מחוורתא רבי
ישמעאל כרבי מאיר סבירא ליה. Machvarta Rabbi Yishmael keRabbi Meir svira lei.
It sounds like, you know, the best explanation is So רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael holds like רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, דחייש למיעוטא, dechaish lemiuta,
he's concerned for minority. Now let me remind you what that case
was. Right, there's first the question about when is it ודאי vadai
a בכור, bechor, and then the question is when does it get
to be ודאי vadai not a בכור. bechor, And then there's the
middle area of ספק. safek? So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says if
this goat gave birth when it was more than a year old,
then it is not a ודאי בכור, vadai bechor. it is a
ספק. safek. Welcome back, חיים. Chaim.
So it is not a ודאי בכור, vadai bechor? it is a
ספק. safek. So the גמרא Gemara says, well why is it called
a ספק? safek. Why don't we put it in the category of
ודאי vadai not? Because we should say that goats that give birth
in their second year, the majority of them have already given birth
before. And let's go by majority and say that it's ודאי vadai
not a בכור, bechor, not a ספק. safek. גמרא gemara, says no,
there's a small possibility, right, there's a מיעוט miut that it has
that it is the first, and therefore רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, is
like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and is concerned with that מיעוט. miut.
So there רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael? was not willing to say it's
ודאי vadai not, he said it is maybe it's a doubt, it's
a ספק. safek, So you see he's concerned with the מיעוט. miut.
So here too, be concerned with the מיעוט. miut. How can you
say, ach, I don't care about the possibility of miscarriage? You're the
one that's concerned about those minority possibilities, and maybe there's a miscarriage,
and it had a miscarriage, and maybe therefore it's not ודאי vadai
בכור, bechor, maybe again it's ספק. safek. Right, the more you're concerned
with, if you think about them, right, definitely a בכור, bechor definitely
not, and this big category in the middle of ספק. safek, The
more you're concerned for מיעוט, miut, for tiny possibilities, you're going to
be pulling stuff from those two end categories into the middle. So
the same way yesterday he pulled it from the definitely not into
the middle category, here too he should pull it from the definitely
is a בכור bechor, into this middle doubt category because maybe it
had a miscarriage. So the גמרא gemara says, כי חייש לחומרא, לקולא
לא חייש. ki chaish lechumra, lecula lo chaish. Very interesting answer. When
is he concerned for a minority? When it means to be מחמיר
machmir and to be safe, not when it means to be מיקל.
meikel. Now we are all very familiar with that mentality and that
type of an approach, right, which is like, oh, there's a small
doubt, let's play it safe. Okay, now but what that means is
there's a whole discussion תוספות Tosafot has, which is, is the position
of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who's concerned for a minority,
is that דאורייתא de'oraita or דרבנן? derabbanan? Is it biblically you really
can ignore the minority, but rabbinically we want to play it safe,
or is it even biblically you have to attend to the minority?
This makes it sound like it's all rabbinic, that biblically you just
ignore it, and but rabbinically we're going to pay attention. Why would
we pay attention? Because we want to be safe, we want to,
you know, cover our bases. So therefore, that's what it sounds like.
When it's in the category that you would say definitely not a
בכור, bechor what does definitely not a בכור bechor, mean? You don't
even have to wait for it to have a מום. mum. You
just eat it right away. Ah, play it safe. We're going to
wait for you to have a מום. mum. We're not taking it
away from you, we're not giving it to the כהן, Kohen. just
play it safe, wait for it to have a מום. mum, That's
when it gave birth in its second year. And therefore we're going
to pull it into the ספק, safek play it safe. We're going
to be חושש למיעוטא. choshesh lemiuta. Here when it's definitely its first
year, give it and as I when it's in its first year,
we say, oh,
95% likelihood it's a בכור, bechor. give it to the כהן. Kohen.
Ah, 5% maybe it's not a בכור. bechor Yeah, but that's not
playing it safe and being מחמיר. machmir. So therefore, since that wouldn't
lead to be מחמיר, machmir, we say do the more better thing
with it, give it to the כהן. Kohen I want to point
out that it's not so clear that it's not being מחמיר, machmir,
right? Because look at what happens. I'm going to treat it as
a ודאי vadai בכור bechor, and give it to a כהן. Kohen
What's the כהן Kohen, going to do with it? He's going to
bring it as a קרבן. korban, Well, if I was really super
פרום, frum, I would say, hey, you know, maybe this thing isn't
a בכור, bechor, and it's חולין בעזרה! chullin ba'azarah! And if I
keep it and I wait for it to get a מום, mum,
then that's definitely playing it safe. I've got all my bases covered.
So it's interesting that the גמרא gemara calls this it's not being
מחמיר machmir because on the one hand it's being מחמיר machmir in
the sense of it's playing it safe to ensure no transgression, but
on the other hand it's not in the sense I am taking
it away from doing something better with it. I am taking it
away from the קרבן, korban. I'm preventing the כהן Kohen, from getting
it. Those are sort of the ideal things to be done with
it. So you have to understand here that it's actually you have
to understand that again, the idea of concern for the minority is
just a rabbinic concern. Because if it were like דאורייתא, de'oraita, of
course you would have to play it safe. But if it's דרבנן,
derabbanan, we could say, look, you're really allowed to go by the
majority. So here where it goes to the כהן, Kohen, that's the
best thing to do with it. Give it to the כהן, Kohen.
don't be worried about the possibility of miscarriage. In the other case
where we would have said keep it and eat it with its
מום, mum, we could say play it safe. But here we don't
want to say play it safe and derail it. Here give it
to the כהן, Kohen do because we really don't have to מעיקר
הדין, me'ikar hadin, you know, be worried about the minority. So that's
the first answer the גמרא Gemara says, this חשינן למיעוטא chashinan lemiuta
is only a side concern and therefore we'll play it safe when
anyway you're keeping it, but we're not going to do it to
take it away from the כהן. Kohen Yeah.
You say that, you know, give it to the כהן Kohen? and
he makes it a קרבן. korban. Do you mean that you can
really actually give it to your local כהן Kohen. and he has
to worry about bringing it up, or you have to worry about
bringing it up and then giving it to a כהן?
Kohen No, no, no, no, no. It's totally his responsibility. You give
it to whoever you find him and it's from there on it's
his responsibility.
So I don't have to bother going to ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Absolutely not.
Okay.
All right. So. That's the first answer, that yes, he's concerned for
the minority, but it's only sort of a, you know, it's a
פרומקייט frumkeit type of a thing, it's a חומרא chumra thing, and
therefore do it when any, you know, anyway you'd keep it, but
don't do it to the point that it's going to take it
away from the כהן. Kohen, If you want another way to frame
it, that would be a חומרא האתי לידי קולא. chumra ha-ati lidei
kula. You'd be מחמיר machmir one way, but you'd be taking it
away from being the בכור, bechor. and therefore you really can rely
on the majority. So that's one way of explaining why Rabbi Ishmael
is not concerned for the miscarriage possibility, because in general we don't
have to be concerned for those tiny possibilities.
What's up with the חולדה? chulda? חולדה chulda was a pretty big
deal.
It is a pretty big deal, but that's why I'm telling you
it's not a real ספק. safek Meaning, it starts by saying that
it's not ספק, safek it's a מיעוט, miut, and really you can
go by majority. So the whole issue of חיישינן למיעוטא chayshinen le-miuta
is only, you know, it's better to play it safe. Okay, but
you don't, you're not really required to, so don't take that approach
if it's going to mean taking it away from the
כהן kohen, and not having it כפרה as a קרבן. korban. Okay,
so that's one answer. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'it eima, and if you want
you could say, you know what, you're right. בין לקולא בין לחומרא
חייב. Bein lekula bein lechumra chayav. That we would have to be
concerned whether to be strict and tell you don't eat, wait till
it has a מום, mum. or whether to be lenient, lenient in
the sense of whether to prevent it from going to the כהן,
kohen prevent it from being brought as a קרבן. korban. Either way,
we would pay attention to the minority and treat it as a
ספק safek. and say you hold on to it, wait for it
to be a blemish. So then why isn't he concerned with miscarriage?
So let's take a look. והכא במתנפת וחוזרת ויולדת בתוך שנתה קמיפלגי.
Ve-hacha be-mitanefet ve-chozeret ve-yoledet betoch shenata kamifligi. The question is, do we
believe that that scenario is possible? Do we believe that an animal
will miscarry, again talking about the goat, transfer this idea to the
sheep, etc.? The goat that we say, remember, gave birth in its
first year, and Rabbi Ishmael said, oh, it's definitely the first birth.
And Rabbi said, well, maybe it miscarried earlier. So maybe his position
is, if it had a miscarriage this year, it would not have
given birth this year. Okay, it doesn't give birth within the same
year that it miscarries. Okay, now that maybe you could understand within
one year by the goat, because maybe that's too close of time.
The funny thing is, is that what about the sheep, let's say
two years? You'd have to say if it gave, if it miscarried,
it won't give birth until after, but the after the, but presumably
the reason we're saying a sheep if it has birth in the
second year, it's a first birth, is because it can't, right, get
pregnant or even have a miscarriage, presumably, I don't know exactly what
they thought, but presumably till the beginning of the second year. So
since it can only be first get pregnant in its second year,
any miscarriage would have happened in its second year, and then he's
saying it can't both miscarry and give birth within the same year.
And the same by the cow, any pregnancy would have begun in
the third year, it can't both miscarry and give birth within that
one year time. Okay, so that's what Rabbi Ishmael says. Yes, miscarriage
is possible, but then it won't give birth, and I still assert
that if it's given birth, it had no prior pregnancy. Okay, so
that's maybe what he holds. Rabbi Ishmael סבר מתנפת אינה חוזרת ויולדת
בתוך שנתה. savar mitanefet eina chozeret ve-yoledet betoch shenata.
If an animal miscarried, it will not go ahead and go back
and give birth during the same year. והא מדאוליד ודאי לא טניף.
Ve-ha mide-olid vadai lo tanif. And from the fact that it gave
birth, it certainly did not miscarry. Rabbi Yehoshua סבר מתנפת חוזרת ויולדת
בתוך שנתה. savar mitanefet chozeret ve-yoledet betoch shenata. If
it can miscarry and then go back and give birth even within
the same year.
So that is the first debate. We've decided that we don't want
to accept the possibility that people, that miscarriage does not exempt, as
Rivka said, פטר רחם peter rechem won't allow for that. We don't
want to say that we ignore the tiny possibility of miscarriage, it's
only a מיעוט, miut, because it seems to be we're concerning ourselves
with מיעוט. miut. But the question is, is that scenario possible of
giving, miscarrying and birth in the same year? Now we get to
Rabbi Yehoshua's own personal opinion, which sounded very much like the opinion
he reported. ואני, and I, איני אומר כן, eini omer ken, I
don't say exactly the way that I just reported, that I got
from my רביים. rebbe'im. אלא, this is the way I say it,
says Rabbi Yehoshua. עז שטנפה בששה יולדת בתוך שנתה. Ez she-tinfah bashisha
yoledet betoch shenata.
If it miscarried in the first six months, then it could give
birth in the first year. רחל שטנפה בשנה יולדת בתוך שתים. Rachel
she-tinfah bashana yoledet betoch shetayim. If a sheep miscarried in the first
year, it will give birth in the second year. So that just
sounds like he's saying it's possible to miscarry, he's just giving more
particulars about the timing. So מאי איכא בין גמריה לסבריה? mai ika
bein gemarei le-savarei? What's the difference between his received tradition, גמרא, Gemara.
what he repeated that he had learned it from his רביים, rebbe'im,
right, it says אבל אמרו aval amru was how it was introduced.
They said, meaning he had received a tradition, which just said generally
what about miscarriage? And his own סברא sevara which gives more specifics
about how the, the timing of the miscarriage and the birth. What's
the נפקא מינה? nafka mina? So the גמרא Gemara says, here's the
נפקא מינה. nafka mina. שטנפה בסוף ששה. She-tinfah besof shisha. That it
miscarried at the end of six months. ואיכא בינייהו דזעירי, Ve-ika beinaihu
de-Ze'iri, and it hinges on זעירי. Ze'iri. Let's say this out and
then we'll explain. דאמר זעירי, De-amar Ze'iri, זעירי Ze'iri says, אין טינוף
פחות משלושים
יום. ein tinuf pachot mishloshim yom. That an animal after it miscarries
does not, this is not the literal meaning of the words, but
this is what it means, after it miscarries will not conceive or
will not copulate within thirty days after the miscarriage. Okay, so here's
the scenario. this goat, okay, miscarried in the beginning of the seventh
month. Now, if you hold like זעירי, Zeiri, okay, that means that
it won't be able to become to conceive or copulate till the
beginning of the eighth month. Now it takes five months to give
birth, so you have eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve, but it only
conceived in the beginning of the eighth month, so it'll only give
birth in the second year. Okay, so therefore, since what, so therefore,
since what Yehoshua says is, Yehoshua says if it miscarried prior to
the end of the sixth month, then this birth that you've seen
could be, is possible, right, within the first year. If it miscarried
after the end of the sixth month, then it's not possible to
give birth within the first year. So how will this play out?
Let's take a look. Okay, לגמרא אית ליה דזעירי, le-Gemara it lei
de-Zeiri, לסברא לית ליה דזעירי. le-svara leit lei de-Zeiri.
So according to his tradition they hold of זעירי, Zeiri, according to
his סברא svara he does not hold of זעירי. Zeiri. What does
this mean? So hold on, let me just check Rashi again, make
sure I'm saying this over correctly.
Okay, so, okay, so he's saying like this. He's saying the point
is, let's say the scenario that we saw that this animal miscarried,
did not miscarry earlier, so somehow it's a scenario where you've been
watching this animal and you see that it did not miscarry earlier
in its life and you only saw it miscarry into the seventh
month. Okay, and then you saw it give birth within the first
year. Okay, so in that type of a case, how does that
work? We just said that you know that that's sort of not
possible, right, because if it gave birth, if it miscarried into the
seventh month, it would have to wait a month until it became
pregnant, it couldn't give birth in the first year. So what, so
if you hold that that really is the is the is the
like so if you hold that that really is part of the
rules, you know, is the science, then you would say that the
fact that it looked like it miscarried wasn't a real miscarriage and
that this thing that gave birth was really the first birth.
That's if you, that's if you agree with זעירי. Zeiri. If you
agree with זעירי Zeiri then you're looking at this, by the way
it's another great example, right, about how you reinterpret the facts based
on your principles. So if your principles was it couldn't have given
birth in this scenario because the miscarriage was after six months and
it gave birth within the first year, then you say, ah, it
must be it didn't really have a miscarriage and that this really
is the first birth and it's חייב בבכור. chayav be-bechor. If however
you say that you don't have those scientific principles, then you'll say
it did have a miscarriage and this animal is not a בכור.
bechor. Okay, so that's what we're saying, that there's not a difference
when you have not been observing it, until now we've been talking
about animals you haven't been observing and you're trying to figure out
whether it's the firstborn, the נפקא מינה nafka mina is when you
have been observing it and you see this miscarriage in the seventh
month and then you see a birth, can you assume it's the
first, it was not a real miscarriage or you have and it
is a first birth or not? So let's take, let's read that
again. So לגמרא, le-Gemara, according to his tradition, אית ליה דזעירי, it
lei de-Zeiri, they hold of זעירי Zeiri and that would basically say
that it would, that this would be a not a real miscarriage
and that this animal would be what do you call it, would
be a firstborn. לסברא, le-svara, according to his סברא, svara,
then לית ליה דזעירי, leit lei de-Zeiri, doesn't hold of זעירי Zeiri
and therefore this animal actually the first thing actually would have been
a miscarriage and this actually would be would not be considered a
firstborn. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, if you want you could say דכולי
עלמא אית להו דזעירי, de-kulei alma it lehu de-Zeiri, everybody holds
of זעירי, Zeiri, והכא ביולדת למקוטעין קמיפלגי, ve-hacha be-yoledes le-mikutain kamifligi, whether
when we say an animal gives birth in five months, whether it
has to be five full months. Can animals give birth into the
fifth month? Okay,
והתניא, ve-hatanya, so
did I skip a line? I think I turned to the wrong
page, I'm sorry.
Yes, לגמרא, le-Gemara, according to his tradition, לא אמרינן יולדת למקוטעין, lo
amrinan yoledes le-mikutain, it doesn't give birth in partial months.
לסברא, le-svara, אמרינן יולדת למקוטעין, amrinan yoledes le-mikutain, it does give birth
partial months. What does this mean? Again the same scenario, that it
miscarried in the seventh month, okay, and it gave birth within a
year. Now how is that possible? It had to wait a month
if we hold of זעירי, Zeiri, it had to wait a month
to become pregnant and then five months to give birth. Ah, do
you need five full months or not five full months? Okay, so
according to his tradition it could not have given birth למקוטעין, le-mikutain,
so if it. According to his סברא, svara, it's possible that it
gives birth within the fifth month, not five full months, so then
how could this happen? It must be that it really was not
a miscarriage, right? Because if it really was a miscarriage, and it
needed five full months, it couldn't have given birth till the seventh.
According to his סברא, svara, it's possible that it gives birth within
the fifth month, not five full months, and therefore we assume it
was a real miscarriage and you're not obligated. אי בעית אימא, Ee
ba'it eima, if you want, לאו אמינא ילדת למקוטעין, lav amina yaledet
l'mekuta'in, and nobody says it can be somewhere in the middle of
the fifth month, but הכא במקצת
היום ככולו, hacha b'miktzat hayom k'kulo, like trying to apply halakhic categories
to biological reality, the question is anywhere in the fifth month is
not possible, but how about the last day of the fifth month?
Would we say that the last day of the fifth month, since
it's a partial day, it's like it's a whole day, and therefore
it's like it had the five full months? Okay, so this goat
would be an animal that miscarried one day into the seventh month,
you hold like זעירי, Zeiri, so it could not have become pregnant
for a month later, then it needs five months to give birth,
so it really could only have given birth on the first day
of the second year, but it gave birth on the last day
of the first year. Is that an indication that the prior miscarriage
wasn't a miscarriage or not, because or else it couldn't have given
birth within this time period? Ah, but maybe it could, maybe you
don't need five full months, maybe the last day counts as the
full day and therefore it's like it was a full five months.
Okay, so לסברה אמינא מקצת היום ככולו, l'savreh amina miktzat hayom k'kulo,
according to his own סברא svara we say the partial day is
like the full day, and therefore the fact it gave birth on
the last day is still a possibility and the miscarriage was genuinely
a miscarriage and it's not a בכור. bechor לגמרא, l'gmara, according to
his גמרא, Gemara לא אמינא מקצת היום ככולו, lo amina miktzat hayom
k'kulo, it's not possible, and therefore how did it give birth within
the first year? The only way, since it needed five full months,
was that the miscarriage really wasn't a miscarriage. Okay, so that is
a lot of theoretical possibilities of distinguishing. The basic פשט pshat of
it is that both his own tradition and the way he articulated
agree that the problem here is that whether an animal, they both
say you cannot assume if an animal gave birth within a certain
time frame it's the first birth, maybe there was a miscarriage, except
his own סברא svara was more articulate about what is the scenario
of the miscarriage, right, that if it happens within six months then
it can become pregnant again, and that led us to speculate about
ways in which a totally different set of cases where we observed
the whole thing, and therefore knowing this way in which you assume
an animal miscarries and then is able to give birth, does it
allow us to assume that what we saw wasn't a real miscarriage?
Okay, but the basic argument in terms of the משנה Mishnah. still
is that you can't say that a birth is definitely a בכור
bechor, because of the possibility of an earlier miscarriage. Yes.
What is זעירי, Zeiri, is that a person? זעירי Zeiri is a
person's name, yes, that's the opinion,
that's the opinion that an animal needs to wait a month after
miscarriage before becoming pregnant. Okay. All right, so that was interesting, trying
to base on whether it did give birth to backwards figure out
whether it was a real miscarriage or not. Now we go to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who seems to argue more categorically. אמר לו
רבי עקיבא אני לא באתי לידי מידה זו, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva
ani lo bati lidei middah zo,
I haven't, you know, I'm not so smart as you, is sort
of what he's saying a little ironically, because I'm not so smart
like this, I don't know about, you know, first year, second year,
I know that if it's ודאי vadai, yes, it's to the כהן,
kohein. ודאי vadai no it's
not, ספק safek. you keep it from him, which is of course
what everybody holds, except they think there's a way to figure it
out sometimes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מאי איכא בין רבי
עקיבא לרבי יהושע? mai ika bein Rabbi Akiva l'Rabbi Yehoshua? What's their
difference? I mean, does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva just like not try
to pay attention to these issues about what year it gave birth
and possibility of miscarriage? So what's he really say? So אמר רבי
חנינא מסורא, Amar Rabbi Chanina mi-Sura, חלב פוטר איכא בינייהו. chalav poter
ika beinihu. How about if the animal is lactating? We haven't seen
it miscarry but it's lactating. Is that evidence of prior birth? Okay,
now you would think pretty much ah yes. I actually had the
opportunity to check this on the internet, the question is is there
ever cases of hormonal imbalance that lead to lactation without birth? I
have no idea. I would imagine it was possible. I mean Dvora
told me that there are cases where a woman can adopt children
and start lactating.
Yeah, right, so I imagine it's possible hormonal imbalance can
lead in some rare cases to lactation.
So here we're not, until now we've been debating the following: is
it ודאי vadai. to the כהן Kohein because it wouldn't have given
birth, or is it a ספק safek? because of the possibility of
miscarriage, we're sort of at this end of the ספק. safek Now
we're asking about this end of the ספק. safek, You see an
animal lactating and then it gives birth to an animal, to a
child. So the normal person would say it's ודאי vaday the second
child, it's totally in that category, eat it without a מום. mum.
But do you say wait maybe, right, maybe there's a small possibility
it was lactating without having given birth and therefore this animal is
also a ספק? safek. Well okay, so let's take a look. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara wants to say that's maybe the debate. Let's
see how it spells it out. רבי עקיבא סבר Rabbi Akiva savar
חלב פוטר, chalav poteir,
the milking exempts. הלכה אחר רוב בהמות, halacha achar rov behemos, go
by the majority of animals. רוב בהמות אין חולבות אלא אם כן
ילדו, rov behemos ein cholvos ela im kein yaldos, most animals do
not milk, lactate, unless they've given birth, and therefore
he's
willing to call that ודאי, vaday you know, ודאי the second animal.
And therefore you don't even have to wait for a blemish. רבי
יהושע סבר, Rabbi Yehoshua savar, and Rabbi Yehoshua holds, האי איכא מיעוטא
דחולבות, hai ika miyuta decholvos,
there's a minority that lactate אף על פי שאין יולדות, af al
pi she'ein yoldos, even without having given birth, and therefore that case
would be considered a ספק safek. and you'd have to wait for
it to be a מום. mum. So the גמרא Gemara asks exactly
what Michael asked: ומי חייש רבי יהושע למיעוטא? u'mi chaish Rabbi Yehoshua
lemiuta? Actually, I mean now before we had said the whole debate
of, you know, רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, who was it,
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua was רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael, was concerned for the מיעוט miut and רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua was not, and here we're going to actually prove explicitly
that he is not concerned with that. Of course that's a little
bit funny because what about the whole issue about miscarriage? But let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara ומי חייש רבי יהושע למיעוטא,
u'mi chaish Rabbi Yehoshua lemiuta, is he really concerned for a minority?
והתנן, vehatnan, we taught in a משנה. היתה לה חמותה. haysah lah
chamossah. So now a woman is married to a man and he
dies without kids, but no brother, so there's no need for יבום.
yibbum. Only problem was was that she has a mother-in-law that she
left back, you know, in some place a thousand miles away, and
maybe by the time, since she's left her mother-in-law and before her
husband died, her mother-in-law had a son. So now she does have
a brother-in-law she doesn't know about. Does she have to worry about
the possibility that she has a brother-in-law she doesn't know about? היתה
לה חמותה, haysah lah chamossah, she has a mother-in-law, אינה חוששת, einah
chosheshes, she doesn't have to be concerned that sometime even in the
last 10 years that maybe her mother had another child and she
has an unknown brother-in-law. יצאת מלאה, yatzas mele'ah, however, if her mother-in-law
left them or she left her, it doesn't matter, when she was
pregnant,
so then it's reasonably possible that she does have a brother-in-law, then
חוששת, chosheshes, then she has to be concerned, has to find out
before she can assume that she's free without
חליצה. chalitzah. רבי יהושע אומר אינה חוששת, Rabbi Yehoshua omer einah chosheshes,
she doesn't have to worry. That seems pretty wild, right? Why? So
listen to this. ורמינן, v'raminan, מאי טעמא דרבי יהושע, mai ta'ama deRabbi
Yehoshua, why is he not concerned with the brother-in-law possibility? קסבר, kasavar,
he's of the opinion, רוב מעוברות יולדות, rov me'ubaros yoldos, majority of
pregnant women have successful live births, ומיעוט מפילות, umiut mapilos, there's some
that miscarry. וכל היולדות, vechol hayoldos, so let's say 95% of births
in that time was probably less than 95%, let's say 95% of
births were live, and of those 95%, מחצה זכרים ומחצה נקבות, mechetza
zacharim u'mechetza nekeivos, 50% boys 50% girls. So what's the likelihood she
has a live brother-in-law? Only about 45%. So it's a מיעוט, miut,
you don't have to be concerned about. Now that's wild normally when
you're not concerned about a מיעוט miut we say you mean 5%,
10%, 45%? But no, she doesn't have to be concerned. והוו ליה
זכרים מיעוטא, vehavu lei zacharim miuta, it's a minority, ולמיעוטא לא חיישינן,
ulemiuta lo chaishinan, and we're not concerned. So therefore if he's not
concerned with a 45% possibility, right, how can he all of a
sudden be the one that is concerned that the animal, you know,
that the animal might maybe is lactating without children?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא איפוך, ela ippoich, reverse it. That
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, will say that if it lactates then I'm
not concerned then I definitely know it's given birth, and if it
has a
child we're considered definitely not a בכור, bechor. we don't wait for
a blemish, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, it's still a
ספק, safek, which by the way fits the words of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva better. Because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I don't know
what you're talking about, if it's definitely this way it's one, if
it's definitely that way it's the other, everything sounds like he's basically
saying pretty much everything is a ספק. safek. So any place that
there's any reason of doubt it's a ספק. safek. So he says
even if it's milking, that's the way the גמרא understands, even if
it's milking, I think that that is still a reason to doubt.
But רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no, I don't care about the
minority. ותניא, vesanya, we taught similarly in a ברייתא, Baraisa. חלב פוטר
דברי רבי יהושע, chalav poteir divrei Rabbi Yehoshua, milking exempts totally, there's
not even a doubt. רבי עקיבא אומר חלב אינו פוטר, Rabbi Akiva
omer chalav eino poteir, it does not, so it's explicit in the
ברייתא. braisa Now what is a little bit interesting is that if
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua here is not concerned with the doubt even
45%, then it's pretty funny that he argues on Rabbi, on רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael. right, because even though if you see an animal
give birth first, even though there's a possibility of what do you
call it, of miscarriage, right, but it's a small possibility that it
miscarried prior, right, so why does he bother to argue on רבי
ישמעאל? Now the partial answer is is that again which way are
we,
no that doesn't work, it actually is the opposite, because in the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva case he's not concerned with the מיעוט miut
and he's מקיל, meikil, he doesn't wait for it to be a
מום. mum. In the רבי ישמעאל case he's concerned with the מיעוט
miut and he's being,
and you know it's taking it away from giving it to the
כהן. kohen, Yeah, so it really does not work so well.
תוספות Tosafos tries
to...
Yeah, I mean, it's pretty interesting, right? Because in this case, you
have a חזקה chazakah normally if we went also looked at חזקה
chazakah status quo, so the mother has a status quo of not
having given birth before. Right? So it has a status quo of
not having given birth before to be חושש choshesh to be concerned
for the מיעוט miyut would just be to be playing it safe,
and even so he ignores the חזקה, chazakah, he ignores the מיעוט,
miyut, and he doesn't even ask that you play it safe. That's
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua in the case of milk, right? And nevertheless,
in the possibility of miscarriage, he's willing to be to be he's
willing to be concerned about the minority. Yeah, so first of all,
it seems like רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, a little bit is not
consistent.
And I am trying to remember if תוספות Tosafos directly addresses that,
one second.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so תוספות Tosafos does address it, and he says
one minute, תוספות Tosafos on כ' עמוד א'. Yeah,
so what תוספות Tosafos says is, right, תוספות Tosafos says the following.
תוספות Tosafos says like this: You're right. רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua this
is important because it introduces the fact that you have two different
considerations going here. He says רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, says we're not
concerned for the minority, and therefore we're willing to say even if
this animal's black-pating, you don't have to worry at all, and you
don't even have to wait for it to be a מום. mum.
So why is he concerned about the miscarriage? So תוספות Tosafos says
like this: He's not concerned about the he's not saying that I'm
concerned about the miscarriage הלכתית. halachically. I'm concerned you're going to bring
חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, would say I'm not
I'm not חייש chaish the מיעוט miyut of 45%, 45% I'm not
concerned, I let this woman remarry. So really I would let you
go ahead and bring this animal as a קרבן. korban, That's not
my point. My point is because there's a tiny possibility, there's another
lens to bring here, not the איסור קרבן issur korban lens, but
the ממונות mamonos lens. And remember the principle in דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos is המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. And when
we say the other guy has the burden of proof, there, even
if the majority is on his side, if you want to extract
money from me, you really need to prove it beyond any reasonable
doubt. So therefore, in this case, where the animal gave birth and
you're saying, oh, but maybe there was a miscarriage and there's a
possibility of a miscarriage prior, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, would say like
this: Me, the ישראל, if I wanted to bring this animal as
a קרבן, korban right, maybe תוספות Tosafos isn't sure about this, but
maybe I would actually say I have to bring it as a
קרבן korban. because I'm not concerned for the minority and I have
to assume it's a בכור. bechor But you're that's from the world
of איסור והיתר issur veheter and what do you do with this,
does it have קדושה kedushah or not. But you want to come
and you're the כהן and tell me I have to give it
to you, I say prove that there wasn't a miscarriage prior. Because
the rule the rules that govern דיני ממונות dinei mamonos are different
than the rules that govern like איסור. issur. And therefore for דיני
ממונות, dinei mamonos, you need to really prove it, and the small
possibility of a miscarriage means that you can't extract it from me.
But the rules that govern איסור והיתר issur veheter would say we
ignore that, we let a woman remarry, we're not concerned about a
huge 45% possibility, and therefore here too we wouldn't we would assume
if it were not for the דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, we would
assume that it was a full בכור bechor bring his a קרבן.
korban? Now the one point that תוספות Tosafos is left with, and
this is Michael's קשיא, kushya, can you really פסקן pasken in contradictory
ways on the same animal? Can I say I don't have to
give it to you, but when I ask myself what do I
do with it, I have to treat it like a בכור bechor,
and I can't shear it and I can't work it and I
bring it as a קרבן? korban So I have to bring it
as a קרבן korban, and I treat it as a בכור, bechor,
but in דיני ממונות dinei mamonos I say it's not. So תוספות
Tosafos thinks it's possible that דיני ממונות dinei mamonos will dictate, which
is quite interesting. That since in דיני ממונות dinei mamonos you can't
prove it's yours and I'm allowed to keep it, therefore, you know,
I get to treat it as a ספק בכור safek bechor and
not a ודאי.
And even if I wanted to bring it to the עזרה, azarah,
and even if I wanted to, I can't, I have to wait
for it to have a מום. mum? I have to because since
the דיני ממונות dinei mamonos means you can't prove it and we
treat it as a ספק, that has implications for the איסור. issur.
So that actually is, besides just reconciling רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua I
had wanted to bring that in because I think it really, you
know, is a very important conceptual question that we said this before,
we did this before when we did מתנות כהונה matnos kehunah and
so on, but there there was only the ממונות mamonos aspect. There
there was a doubt, but at the end of the day, all
there really was was just ownership, there wasn't קדושה, kedushah, there wasn't
איסורים. issurim. And here you have two separate things going on and
they go by different standards. So רבי יהושע would say when it
comes to איסור, issur, I completely ignore the minority. I'll let the
woman remarry, you know, you don't have to be concerned, you know,
etc., etc. I completely ignore that. So actually the possibility of a
miscarriage prior should be ignored and it should be a ודאי בכור.
bechor. So why then does he say it's not a ודאי בכור?
bechor. Because דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, the minorities matter, and the person
who's in possession can assume that he has a right to hold
it unless the other guy can prove. And then the interesting question
is to what degree does the דיני ממונות dinei mamonos category transform
the איסור issur category? So if you want to just see quickly,
because we do have an extra minute, actually look at the bottom
of תוספות ס"ח ע"ב. Tosafot samach chet amud bet. I'll read you
just the one line where he raises this question of whether one
influences the other. He says like this. He says,
one minute.
He says like this, ומיהו היא קצת תימה. umihu hi kzat teima.
Right. It is eight lines from the bottom before the one דרבי
יהושע. d'Rabbi Yehoshua. About four lines, eight lines before the new תוספות
לכולא. Tosafot lekula. It starts, the line starts with the word ומיהו.
umihu. So he says like this, ומיהו היא קצת תימה דלעניין מלקות
בגיזה ועבודה ולעניין להקריבו על המזבח חשיב ודאי בכור. umihu hi kzat
teima d'le'inyan malkos begiza va'avoda ule'inyan lehakrivo al hamizbeach chashiv vaday bechor.
This is when he was saying they would influence. So therefore, I'm
not going to be concerned about the minority when it comes to
איסור. issur. So if I use this animal, I would get lashes.
If I brought, I could bring it to the altar. Let's assume
this is where רבי יהושע, the possibility of the prior miscarriage. So
therefore, I'm not חייש למיעוטא. chaish lemiuta. So therefore, if I would
misuse it, I would get lashes. If I wanted to bring it
to the altar, I could assume it's definitely a בכור, bechor right?
דאזלינן בתר רובא וחזקה. d'azlinan basar ruba vachazaka. There you go by
majority and חזקה. chazaka. ולעניין ליתנו לכהן, ule'inyan litno l'kohen, but to
give it to you, the כהן, יחשב ספק. yechashev safek. Then they
go, oh, maybe it's not a בכור. bechor So if I want
to go ahead and bring it as a קרבן, that I'm allowed,
I don't have to be concerned. If I misused it, you'd give
me lashes. But all of a sudden, somebody wants it from me
and I say maybe it's not a בכור. Okay, so it's a
little funny that those two categories should not influence one another. Okay,
and he says,
okay,
then he has another answer. So he doesn't really have an answer
to that. But I suggested, although it's interesting, תוספות Tosafot himself is
not willing, and I may be misstated it, תוספות Tosafot himself is
not willing to go so far to suggest that the דיני ממונות
dinei mamonos would influence the איסור issur question. Okay, but that is
interesting. Can you have different statuses based on which category you apply
it to? Now, some אחרונים acharonim point out that דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos is always influencing the איסור issur question because if, you know,
Seth says I owe him money and I say maybe I don't,
and I don't even remember, maybe I do, maybe I don't, so
we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hareaya. Well, why
don't we say, but if I owe him the money and I'm
not giving it to him, it's ספק גזל, safek gezel, you know,
that I'm holding on to money that doesn't belong to me? So
there we always say, but that's an איסור issur that's about ממונות.
mamonos. So there we say you deal with it from the civil
perspective and that determines whether the איסורים issurim relating to ownership are
relevant or not. Here, they're really completely separate categories and can you
come to one conclusion in one area and another conclusion in another
area? Okay, so that is רבי יהושע, that he's not concerned for
מיעוט. miut. That's what we say here, and he's not concerned about
the animal that is, that's lactating, that definitely has given birth before,
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is. So now to review where we
are. You have an animal, you have one side of the spectrum
which is it definitely is firstborn. What's that case? So according to
רבי ישמעאל, it's that it gave birth within a year for a
goat or two years for a sheep. Why aren't we concerned about
miscarriages? Because basically, either in general he's not concerned for מיעוט miut
or more, what's more likely and better, is the fact that it
wouldn't have miscarried and given birth in the same year. That's רבי
ישמעאל. Comes along רבי יהושע, he is concerned for that possibility, he
treats that as a ספק. Now you get to this end of
the spectrum. What would be considered a ודאי not בכור that you
don't even have to wait for a מום? So here רבי יהושע
says that if it's lactating and then gives birth, it's ודאי not
a בכור and I'm not concerned for the minority. And רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says no, even that case I'm going to be concerned.
Anything I don't know absolutely certain is in the ספק. The other
two categories are very, very small. You have to know absolutely for
certain.
Okay, now the גמרא continues.
תנו רבנן גדייה שילדה שלוש
בנות וכל בנותיה הולידו בנותיה ילדו שלוש שלוש.
tanu rabanan gedya sheyalda shalosh banos vechol bnoseha
holidu bnoseha yaldu shalosh shalosh.
Now remember, goats give birth within a year and they have a
five-month pregnancy cycle, five-month cycle. So therefore, it's possible for it to
become a grandmother all within the first year, right? It gave birth
in five, at you know, at five months, six months, whatever, then
its kids, you know, immediately became pregnant and gave birth and within
the first year it could be a grandmother, okay, because the cycle
is five months. So it had three kids and all of its
kids had שלוש שלוש, shalosh shalosh, had three kids, all within one
year. כולן נכנסות לדיר להתעשר. kulan nichnasos ladir lehisaser. You take all
the mothers and grandmothers and you take מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema. מעשר
בהמה ma'aser behema is everything that was born within a year. So
within one year you had twelve animals, right? The three first of
the second generation and then each one of them had three, nine,
twelve. So all of them you take
מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behema. Okay, so now, למה לי למיתני lama li
l'misni שלוש שלוש? shalosh shalosh?
So the
first גמרא says why did it have to give the scenario of
three three? תוליד חדא מינייהו תלת ואינך תרתי תרתי. tolid chada mineihu
tlas v'inach tarti tarti. You know, you're going overboard. Say that of
the kids, one had another three and the other two each one
had two and that would still get you ten. So right, three,
five, seven, ten. Got it? Okay, so גמרא says איידי דאיכא חדא
דלא סגיא בלא שלוש, aidi d'ika chada d'lo sagya b'lo shalosh,
since we had to say one of the kids had three kids
herself, so תנא כולהו tana kulhu שלוש שלוש. shalosh shalosh. So to
get ten, which is what we're trying to do, we had to
have one of the kids having three, so therefore we said that
all of them had three. ולמה לי למיתני שלוש v'lama li l'misni
shalosh כלל? klal? Why do you need anybody getting three? ליהוו כולהו
תרתי, leihavu kulhu tarti, that all of those three have two. So
now how many do you have? Three plus six is nine, right?
To get ten, the mother doesn't have מעשר, maiser, מעשר maiser is
only the newly born. Ah, but while the kids are having kids,
ותהדר איהי ותוליד בהדייהו, v'seihadar ee v'tolid bahadeiyum, the mother gets pregnant
again and the mother has a second crop of kids. Okay, so
you can have a scenario of ten without it being so many
multiple births.
So the גמרא says לימא קסבר, leima kasavar, since it does not
give this scenario, let's say it holds מטנפת metanefes אינה חוזרת ויולדת
eina chozeres v'yoledes בתוך שנתה. Similar to what we said before, that
when an animal miscarries it doesn't give birth again the same year.
This isn't miscarriage, but it's the same born. Its birth doesn't give
birth again in the same year,
so we didn't give the scenario of the mother giving birth again.
We gave the scenario of all the kids each having three. So
אי? ee? So the גמרא says no, you can't prove it. אם
תמצא לומר im timtza lomar מטנפת חוזרת ויולדת metanefes chozeres v'yoledes בתוך
שנתה, it's possible that after a miscarriage you would have birth again.
אבל יולדת ודאי אינה חוזרת ויולדת בתוך שנתה. aval yoledes vadai eina
chozeres v'yoledes b'toch shnasah. But if you gave birth, it would not
have two live births in the same year. So that's one thing
that's implicitly being taught by this ברייתא braisa other than describing an
interesting scenario is that we don't have to assume it won't happen
that you'll have a second birth within the same year. There might
be a debate whether you'll have a birth after a miscarriage in
a year, but a birth after birth won't happen. Okay, and we
will continue with looking at this ברייתא tomorrow. Who do you understand?
So Rabbi Akiva, so he's not like מסתברא mistabra חושש למיעוטא choshesh
l'miyuta or is חושש?
choshesh? Okay, there, one minute, I want to point out that I
chose the first time.